<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A word to the army, touching their sin and dutie if it may bee, to convince them of the greatness of the one, and their defectiveness in the other : with a word of advice in the conclusion, humbly tendred to them, in order to their recovery to that path of unfeigned repentance / by William Allen, late Adjutant-general to the Army in Ireland ...</title>
            <author>Allen, William, Adjutant-general of the army in Ireland.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 51 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A23655</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A1053</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R20056</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12116383</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12116383</idno>
            <idno type="VID">54315</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A23655)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 54315)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 755:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A word to the army, touching their sin and dutie if it may bee, to convince them of the greatness of the one, and their defectiveness in the other : with a word of advice in the conclusion, humbly tendred to them, in order to their recovery to that path of unfeigned repentance / by William Allen, late Adjutant-general to the Army in Ireland ...</title>
                  <author>Allen, William, Adjutant-general of the army in Ireland.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>20 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Livewell Chapman ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1660.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>England and Wales. --  Army --  Regulations.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:54315:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:54315:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Word to the Army, Touching Their SIN and DUTIE: If it may bee, to convince them of the Greatneſs of the one, and their Defectiveneſs in the other; With a word of Advice in the Concluſion, humbly tendred to them, in order to their Recovery to that Path of Unfeigned Repentance.</p>
            <p>By <hi>William Allen</hi> late Adjutant General to the Army in <hi>Ireland,</hi> an unfeigned ſeeker of their ſouls welfare, being under great fears and thoughts of heart for them.</p>
            <q>Cry aloud, liſt up thy voice like a trumpet, and ſhew my people their tranſgreſſion, and the houſe of Jacob their ſins. <bibl>
                  <hi>Iſa. 58.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>Yet they ſeck mee daily, and delight to know my waies, as a Nation that did righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, and forſook not the Ordinances of their God, they ask of mee the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances of Justice, they take delight in approaching to God. Wherefore have wee fasted, ſay they, and thou ſeeſt not? wherefore have wee afflicted our ſouls, and thou takeſt no knowledge? Behold, in the day of your faſt you finde pleaſure, and exact all your labours; behold you faſt for ſtrife and debate, and to ſmite with the fiſt of wickedneſs, you ſhall not faſt as you do this day, to make your voice to be heard on high.</p>
               <p>Is not this the faſt that I have choſen? to looſe the bands of wickedneſs, to undo the heavy burdens, and to let the oppreſſed go free, and that you break every yoak? is it not to deal thy bread to the hungry, and that thou bring the poor that are caſt out, to thy houſe, when thou ſeeſt the naked, that thou cover him, and that thou hide not thy ſelf from thy own fleſh?</p>
               <p>Then ſhall thy light break forth as the morning, and thy health ſhall ſpring forth ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily, and thy righteouſneſs ſhall go before thee, and the glory of the Lord ſhall bee thy rereward.</p>
               <p>Wherefore the Lord ſaid, For as much as this people draw neer mee with their mouth, and with their lips do honour mee, but have removed their heart far from mee, and their fear towards mee is taught by the precepts of men; therefore be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold I will proceed to do a marvelous work amongſt this people, even a marve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous work and wonder, for the wiſdome of their wiſe men ſhall periſh, and the underſtanding of their prudent men ſhall bee hid, <bibl>
                     <hi>Iſa. 28.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
            </q>
            <q>The wiſe men are aſhamed, they are diſmayed and taken, Lo, they have rejected the Word of the Lord, and what wiſdome is in them? <bibl>
                  <hi>Jer. 9.9.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Livewell Chapman,</hi> at the Crown in <hi>Popes-head-Alley.</hi> 1660</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:54315:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:54315:2"/>
            <head>A VVord to the ARMY, touching their Sin, and Duty, if it may be, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince them of the greatneſs of the one, and their defectiveneſs in the other.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Should not delight in this day of <hi>Publick Calamity</hi> come upon you, to bee <hi>uncovering your nakedneſs,</hi> did I not judge it a duty in order to lead you to the <hi>true covering,</hi> and out of all <hi>falſe ones,</hi> which in vain you <hi>hide under,</hi> in your <hi>defiled ſtate,</hi> rendring your ſelves by ſo doing but the <hi>more naked</hi> in the ſight of God and men, giving enemies more occaſion to rejoyce at you, and incourage themſelves in an evil matter againſt you, ſaying, <hi>They offend not,</hi> becauſe you not onely <hi>have,</hi> but <hi>ſtill do ſin</hi> againſt the Lord, the habitation of Juſtice, and hope of your Fathers, though they that ſay ſo, it may bee too truly, ſhall not go unpuniſht in the end.</p>
            <p>I beſeech you therefore give mee leave, in the bowels of love and meekneſs, a little to treat with you, as an Army under theſe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct conſiderations, of <hi>chief Commanders,</hi> and <hi>commanded;</hi> for ſo I ſhall ſpeak to you, both as to your ſin, and duty.</p>
            <p>And firſt to you <hi>Commanders,</hi> you have been <hi>concerned</hi> of late years in very <hi>eminent Tranſactions</hi> in Publick Affairs in theſe Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; have <hi>pretended</hi> to a very <hi>great knowledge,</hi> and <hi>ſtrict obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation</hi> of the <hi>Lord,</hi> and his <hi>goings,</hi> and <hi>doings,</hi> in the midſt of us, with what hee yet <hi>intended</hi> to <hi>do further</hi> in the latter daies; and by comparing his works with his word, have often ſaid, you judge his deſign to <hi>bee the exaltation of his Son, the Lord Jeſus, and his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt in theſe Nations,</hi> and <hi>removing out of the way what ever hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:54315:3"/>his going on with this work:</hi> As alſo you obſerved his <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> herein to bee <hi>gradual,</hi> cauſing his work <hi>ſmall</hi> in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings, to go and grow <hi>higher</hi> and <hi>higher</hi> by degrees, and more <hi>refined</hi> as it grew, and ſo have <hi>Inſtruments been</hi> hee hath made uſe of, and when they have not had ſpirits <hi>growing up</hi> in light, life, and refinedneſs, with the work, by many ſtrange providences have been ſome on one account, ſome upon another, <hi>laid aſide;</hi> yea ſome of them beginning but a little to <hi>ſlack</hi> their pace, and <hi>draw back,</hi> have not ſtayed in that <hi>retrograde motion,</hi> till they have <hi>joyned</hi> with the moſt <hi>avowed enemies</hi> to the <hi>Bleſſed Cauſe</hi> at firſt they were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged in, ſo <hi>dangerous</hi> a thing is <hi>drawing back.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And while you were thus <hi>rightly obſerving</hi> the works and word of the Lord, and helpt to follow it accordingly, being <hi>little</hi> in your own eyes, and going out in a <hi>spirit of trembling,</hi> you <hi>exalted</hi> your ſelves in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> went on and proſpered; <hi>God was with you, and the ſhout of a King amongſt you,</hi> enemies <hi>feared, fled,</hi> and <hi>fell</hi> before you, and your moſt difficult waies and works were made <hi>plain,</hi> and <hi>eaſie;</hi> and though you walkt in <hi>untrodden-paths,</hi> you were carried on <hi>ſafely;</hi> enemies <hi>envying,</hi> yet <hi>dreading</hi> you; friends <hi>rejoycing,</hi> and <hi>bleſsing God</hi> for you, and you from him in his name; and though it muſt bee remembred to the praiſe of the Lord, and due abaſement of Inſtruments, you ſometimes <hi>walkt as men,</hi> eſpecially when you <hi>lean'd to your own underſtandings,</hi> and did <hi>not truſt in the Lord,</hi> as before; Particularly in 47, in your <hi>tampe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings with the King,</hi> and his intereſt, which lead into <hi>thoſe Laby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinths</hi> (as you may well remember) in 48. out of which, nothing but the wiſdome of the Lord directing to ſeeking him, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulting your duty according to his word could extricate you, as was eminently experienc'd in that not to bee forgotten meeting at <hi>Winſor</hi> 48. ſee the memorial of it; and how the Lord lead that year, yea ſeveral years after even to <hi>Woreeſter</hi> fight, by a graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous guiding preſence of his, you cannot but remember that were wiſe obſervers of the operations of his hand: and after that fight, when you were returned in ſafety, you then alſo <hi>ſeemed</hi> to have upon your hearts, a <hi>great ſenſe of your duty,</hi> in proſecuting the work of the Lord you had been employed in, but found as you judged the Parliament unwilling to go ſo faſt, or rather hindering and obſtructing you in the ſpeed you were intended to make,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:54315:3"/>upon which, ſome conteſts aroſe between you and them in that point, and you come to ſee as you ſay, a neceſſity of diſſolving them, as men not ſpirited for the further work of the Lord in that day; how clear and true the demonſtration of this neceſſity was, I take not upon mee to judge, ſince you ſo lately (how truly I dare not determine neither) call in queſtion your action afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, and call them to ſit again, ſaying, <hi>The work had not proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red ſince their diſſolution,</hi> which might bee too true, yet the <hi>Cauſe</hi> might rather bee that <hi>greater unfittedneſs</hi> found in you that followed them, who walkt in <hi>more polluted paths,</hi> in which the work of the Lord could not proſper; and this ſeems to mee ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to bee the mind of the Lord, eſpecially when I conſider the work that Parliament, after you had called them, and they ſate again, were employed about, and upon the matter, onely proſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in, <hi>viz.</hi> judging thoſe more groſs turnings aſide from the Lord and his work, that they found amongſt you in the Army, which when they have in ſome meaſure judged, as men not deſigned to, nor delighted in by the Lord to bee uſed much further, they do by ſtrange providential proceedings amongſt them, period them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and in the doing that, alſo well-nigh hazard putting a period to the peace of theſe Nations.</p>
            <p>But you having diſſolved them, as aforeſaid the firſt time, a little Aſſembly of men is called, not in the way, nor after the manner of the Nations, but upon a more ſelect and avowed ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of men fearing God, though I doubt in their choice, the wiſdome of man was too much exerciſed; but being come toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, though they had their weakneſſes as men, not to bee pleaded for, or owned, they ſeem more effectually to proſecute the true ends of Government, <hi>viz. diſcouraging the bad, countenancing the good, attempting to break and remove oppreſſive yoaks, and to aſſert the liberty of the poor people of the Lord, as well as others, on all accounts,</hi> than any before, or ſince, that I have obſerved: But theſe mercies being too great for ſo ungrateful, and ſo unworthy a people as this Nation; together with the Inſtruments weakneſs and inability to bring them forth in that glory and beauty, as God will have his works brought forth in their ſeaſon; as alſo the great Artifice uſed by the Devil, and Inſtruments amongſt themſelves, who acted <hi>Tobiah</hi> and <hi>Sanballats</hi> part, when they could not by
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:54315:4"/>oppoſing the work openly ſo effectually hinder it, come in and pretend, as they of old, to build with them, and thereby cauſe the work to ceaſe, and render both it and the moſt forward work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men a ſcorn and reproach amongſt the Heathen; theſe alſo are ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly (on what grounds, in what manner, and for what ends be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes the Army to conſider) diſſolved; and the names of many of them, whoſe memorial in ages to come ſhall bee <hi>bleſt,</hi> were <hi>caſt out as evil for Righteouſneſs ſake,</hi> and marks † of <hi>Ignominy</hi> and <hi>Reproach</hi> put upon them before all the Nation by ſome of your ſelves or adherents, that knew what would gratifie you, and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued that path accordingly, as your weekly Pamphleter <hi>Needham,</hi> whoſe tongue is no ſlander, uſed, (and ſtill uſes frequently for your ſervice) to do at that day; and you made it much your buſineſs to be raking into, and laying open, <hi>Cham</hi>-like, the infirmities and nakedneſs of your brethren, contrary to that counſel, or rather reproof given in a like caſe in <hi>Obadiah,</hi> from 10, to the 15. com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared with 8, and 9 <hi>verſes,</hi> being a glaſs in which you may ſee your ſelves and actions; I deſire you will look into with tremb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling. <hi>For thy violence againſt thy Brother Jacob, ſhame ſhall co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver thee, and thou ſhalt bee cut off for ever. In the day that THOU STOODEST ON THE OTHER SIDE, in the day that the ſtranger carried away captive his forces, and forreigners entred into his Gates, and caſt lots upon Jeruſalem, EVEN THOU WAST AS ONE OF THEM, but thou ſhouldeſt not have looked on the day of thy Brother, neither ſhouldeſt thou have rejoyced over the children of Judah in the day of their deſtruction: neither ſhouldeſt thou have SPOKEN PROUDLY IN THE DAY OF DI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STRESSE. Thou ſhouldeſt not have entred into the gate of my people, in the day of their calamity, yea thou ſhouldeſt not have look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on their affliction in the day of their calamity, nor have laid hands on their ſubſtance in the day of their calamity, neither ſhouldeſt thou have ſtood in the croſs way, to cut off thoſe that did eſcape, neither ſhouldeſt thou have delivered up thoſe of his that did remain in the day of his diſtreſs. For the day of the Lord is neer upon all the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then; as thou haſt done, it ſhall bee done unto thee, thy reward ſhall return upon thine own head,</hi> Verſ. 8. <hi>Shall I not in that day, ſaith the Lord, even deſtroy the wiſe men out of Edom, and underſtanding out of the Mount of Eſau?</hi> Verſ. 9. <hi>And thy mighty men. O Teman,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:54315:4"/>ſhall bee diſmayd, to the end that every one of the Mount of Eſau may bee cut off by ſlaughter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Your next ſtep you take as a fruit, I fear of your former, was falling back again into the <hi>old exploded way of the Nation;</hi> having too neer a ſimilitude (though a far worſe ground) to their action, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 8.5, 7. You having now departed from that more pure path you were eminently lead to, and bleſt in while you purſued the ends of Righteouſneſs, as you acknowledge; the conſent of the good people in the three Nations, Navies, Armies, Churches flow in to you, and in hopes of what would bee brought out by you, riſe up as one man, and call you bleſſed: But a <hi>King you muſt have,</hi> as the Nations, in nature, though not in name; who alſo is made, I beleeve, in judgement, beyond his own and your intention, too much like him deſcribed, in 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> from the 11th. to the end; but you (as they) will have him in that poſture, and neer that <hi>port of King and Courtiers</hi> formerly, which being ſo annext to this neer ſimilitude, riſes with it in all its <hi>Pompal formalities,</hi> as a Ghoſt out of its grave, to bee once more adored by a company of <hi>dying declining Chriſtians,</hi> and by this means is the hearts and hopes of the prophane Cavileer, and neu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tral ſpirit, and their adherents incouraged, and the ſpirit of the moſt ſincere through the three Nations (except ſuch as could ſay a confederacy) bowed down and dejected: <hi>A Government framed, none knew by whom,</hi> and <hi>impoſed by you the chief Officers,</hi> and your adherents, on the three Nations, Navies, and Armies, without their conſent, unleſs fraudulently, and unfairly gotten: <hi>Addreſſes made and ſent down</hi> to bee ſigned by the Army, not time given for due conſideration or conſultation in a caſe of that kinde; or if ſome did conſider and expreſs their diſſatisfaction, they were pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently either thrown out of their places, or elſe looked on as per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons not fit to bee truſted in them; And I beſeech you conſider, was not this an evil, an high aggravated evil? conſidering its circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances againſt that poſitive Rule, <hi>Luk.</hi> 6.39. <hi>And as you would that men ſhould do to you, do yee alſo to them likewiſe;</hi> It alſo laies you under, like guilt to that, charged 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.8. <hi>Nay, you do wrong, and defraud, and that your Brethren;</hi> As alſo againſt that Rule, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.6. <hi>That no man go beyond, or defraud his Brother in any matter.</hi> To all which add the cryes, calls, tears, and beſeechings of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:54315:5"/>ſome from all parts to you, to ponder your paths, warning you in the Name of the Lord, of the danger of your way, that it was diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſing to the Lord, gratifying to enemies, and grievous to the hearts of his moſt ſincere ones in the three Nations, and yet <hi>you would not hear;</hi> no, though the Lord alſo every morning brought his judgement to light, yet you were as the <hi>unjuſt, that knew no ſhame;</hi> but you <hi>ſleight</hi> thoſe that bore witneſs for the Lord againſt you, and <hi>contemned</hi> the witneſs they bore, ſaying of and to ſome of them, they would have been quiet, had they been uppermoſt, and the cauſe of their diſſatisfaction, was onely becauſe they were not ſo, which your own conſciences could tell you was notoriouſly falſe; but at laſt you proceed to <hi>impriſon</hi> ſome, <hi>baniſh</hi> others into remote Iſlands, <hi>ſnatching</hi> and keeping others <hi>from their precious Relations,</hi> to what prejudice to ſome of them is not deſired to bee further remembred, and with all <hi>art and induſtry,</hi> by frowns, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours, profits, airy honours, indeavour to <hi>debauch</hi> others from their former profeſt principles and practices, of more integrity to God and their Country, and what <hi>woful work</hi> you have helped to make of this kind in City, Country, Churches, by your <hi>King-craft,</hi> and worſe than <hi>Biſhop-like trapannings,</hi> there is ſad cauſe to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member; and I ſhould ſpeak more, had not the Lord ſpoke ſo much; but ſurely <hi>you did not onely ſin,</hi> but <hi>made Iſrael to ſin;</hi> ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filling that ſad word, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 9.16. <hi>For the leaders of the people cauſe them to erre, and they that are lead of them are deſtroyed;</hi> and hereby you <hi>pave a way,</hi> as it were, to the <hi>Lords anger,</hi> which diſcovered it ſelf at home and abroad, at Sea and at Land, amongſt your Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils and Forces, inſomuch as hee who you had ſet up as your Protector in name, was never leſs truly ſo to you, theſe Nations, nor himſelf, than hee was after you had ſo unduly exalted him, and cloathed him with thoſe vain empty names and titles you had given him.</p>
            <p>But you <hi>go on,</hi> as perſons <hi>engaged,</hi> and indeavour to <hi>engage o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,</hi> as faſt as you can, in the <hi>ſame ſnares</hi> with your ſelves, which the places you were in gave you great advantage to do, being chiefeſt Officers, Councillors, yea of the cloſeſt Caball ſome of you, and others of you more ſubordinate, were ready to receive impreſſions from the reſt, and communicate accordingly to thoſe under their charge; by means of which, many, if not moſt of thoſe
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:54315:5"/>
               <hi>filthy, flattering, hypocritical Addreſſes,</hi> were <hi>framed,</hi> and lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle leſs than <hi>impoſed</hi> on Regiments under their commands, and made as <hi>traps</hi> and <hi>ſnares</hi> frequently to <hi>catch</hi> and <hi>weed out</hi> ſuch as could not run to the ſame exceſs with you, without asking a queſtion for conſcience ſake, whereby many poor ſouls for fear of loſing their places, profits, favours, &amp;c. contrary to their conſciences, <hi>bowed down to theſe abominations,</hi> and <hi>engaged</hi> with you (though falſly) <hi>to live and dye</hi> with that poor perſon that was then up, againſt all oppoſers, forgetting the Lord whom you in thoſe paths were oppoſing, and provoking him to his face, thereby to oppoſe you, by taking away your Protector from amongſt you, as hee ſaw good, which ſtroke, with the manner of it (in ſeveral reſpects, not thought fit to mention) taking him away on that remarkable day, the third of <hi>September,</hi> made famous formerly by the Lords eminent owning him and the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my under his command, in two ſignal Victories obtained a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the enemies of the Lord, when hee fought his bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tels on his name and peoples behalf, and hee is now like <hi>Aaron</hi> of old, uncloathed and ſtript of that honour for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly put upon him, not wiſely improved by him to the ſervice of the Lord that gave it; Ah, this ſtroake <hi>ſpake much</hi> to wiſe ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervers, yea <hi>very much</hi> to you that ſurvived to look well to your <hi>next ſteps,</hi> but alaſs, <hi>God ſpeaks once, yea twice, but man regards not,</hi> you <hi>ſtill hold faſt deceit,</hi> and <hi>refuſe to return,</hi> and <hi>wax worſe and worſe deceiving,</hi> and <hi>being deceived;</hi> who could have thought that you, who were uſed to ſay Gods work grew more refined, and ſo muſt Inſtruments, that ſhould bee uſed and proſper in it: that you ſhould bee the Inſtruments to <hi>advance another poor man</hi> to his, your own, theſe Nations hurt, Gods diſhonour, and the diſ-ſervice of that bleſſed cauſe of God (by this and ſuch like means now become a <hi>by-word,</hi> and a <hi>reproach</hi> amongſt the Heathen) that you knew was ſufficiently deſtitute of the Character aforeſaid? but this you do; and the better to cover <hi>your evil</hi> herein, you cloathe him with thoſe Epithites you did, giving occaſion thereby to the poor fawning Sycophant-like ſpirited people in the Nation to ſtrive in ſin to out-ſtrip you, giving thoſe very Epithites, ſome of them, to him, that were due to God onely, <hi>viz. the man of Gods right hand, whom hee had
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:54315:6"/>made ſtrong for himſelf,</hi> with others too much like it; and this perſon, not to mention his merit or right, is advanced by you to a place of the chiefeſt rule and dignity in the head of three Nations, without the fair or free conſent of them, the Armies or Navies; how right this was in the ſight of God or men, judge yee.</p>
            <p>But you proceed in your fraudulent practices, as formerly, to gain conſent, where it is not given, and are helpt herein, by ſome of the poor Prophets of the Land, who now (as of old) lead the Van in this day of Degeneracy, <hi>ſtrengthening the hands of the wicked,</hi> as well as <hi>ſaddening the hearts of the righteous,</hi> according to <hi>Ezek.</hi> 13. ſo that none <hi>returns</hi> from his wickedneſs; and that they may <hi>ſtrengthen</hi> themſelves and you in this <hi>carnal confederacy,</hi> preſent you with the names of an hundred Churches in the lump, that ſo you may not at all ſuſpect your way, having ſuch a number of thoſe who have profeſt to have given up their names to Chriſt, to approve of you therein, and as it were bleſs you in the name of the Lord; and thus you wrap it up, fulfilling that word, <hi>Jer.</hi> 5.30, 31. <hi>A wonderful and horrible thing is committed in the Land, the Prophets propheſe falſly, and the Priests bear rule by their means, and my peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple love to have it ſo, and what will yee do in the end thereof?</hi> And hereby you bring your ſelves by ſuch actions within the verge of that judgement, written in <hi>Prov.</hi> 24.24. <hi>Hee that ſaith to the WICKED, thou art RIGHTEOUS, him ſhall the people CURSE, NATIONS SHALL ABHOR HIM.</hi> I ſhould ſpeak much more here, but that I deſire rather to bee ſilent, the perſon concerned being gone off the ſtage, and I wiſh may keep off, leſt a worſe thing befall him, and many learn by ſuch ſudden caſtings down, as well as liftings up, to know that <hi>the Lord rules in the Kingdomes of this world, giving them to whom hee pleaſes;</hi> and whoeſer walks in pride, hee is able to abaſe, and may ſo know him, as more to know himſelf, and learn the fear of the Lord, that teaches to depart from all iniquity.</p>
            <p>And having ſpoken thus to you <hi>Commanders,</hi> leſt the <hi>infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour rank</hi> of men of all ſorts in the Army, ſhould think them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves innocent, by beholding you ſo guilty, give mee leave to add a word to ſuch.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:54315:6"/>
            <p> And firſt I deſire you will remember that you have <hi>your ſhare of ſin</hi> in theſe things, having been the <hi>leggs</hi> and <hi>hands</hi> by which theſe <hi>miſchiefs</hi> aforeſaid have been acted; ſome of you having <hi>actually ſeiſed</hi> the poor Saints of the Lord, haling to pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and keeping them there, or at leaſt, <hi>ſaying, a confederacy</hi> with thoſe that did ſo, or not bearing a <hi>faithful witneſs,</hi> as be came you againſt it, ſtanding moſt of you under the influence of <hi>ſinful engagements,</hi> ready bent to fulfil the pleaſure of your Rulers more fully in that point, contrary to light, and much ſtruglings in your own conſciences againſt ſuch things, the Lord grant you <hi>repentance</hi> and <hi>pardon</hi> for it, and to beware of any ſuch <hi>engagements</hi> that ſhall be tendred to you in future, (and oh that you had a <hi>little more conſidered</hi> that lately tendred to you, and ſigned by you, about the <hi>conduct of the Army,</hi> which I fear will prove a <hi>ſore ſnare</hi>) and though it will bee ſaid for you in the caſe aforeſaid, that you were under <hi>many temptations,</hi> viz. <hi>fears of frowns,</hi> and <hi>loſs of favours,</hi> as alſo that little <hi>mony due to you for your Arrears,</hi> if you had born your witneſs, or quit your ſtation; all which indeed might have been your <hi>portion,</hi> in <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge of your duty,</hi> yet you not venturing to run ſuch a hazard for the Lord, how have you fallen! below the ſpirits of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, of Engliſh men, of an Army nor mercinary, yea of <hi>Romans,</hi> though Heathens, who valued their <hi>Country,</hi> and the <hi>Common Rights</hi> of it, at a <hi>higher rate;</hi> and by your <hi>ſin,</hi> without <hi>repentance,</hi> are alſo <hi>under</hi> that woe denounced, in <hi>Iſa.</hi> 31.2. <hi>Yet hee alſo is wiſe, and will bring evil, and will not call back his word, but will ariſe againſt the houſe of evil doers, and againſt the HELP of them that work inquity;</hi> and you have <hi>ſinned</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo againſt that Rule, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 8.13. <hi>Say not a confederacy to all them to whom theſe people ſhall ſay a confederacy, neither fear yee their fear, nor bee afraid, but ſanctifie the Lord of Hoſts him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and let him bee your fear, and let him bee your dread;</hi> and let mee beſeech you ſo to ponder the paths of your feet, as to <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent</hi> of what is paſt, and to <hi>take heed</hi> in time to come, that you follow no leader, nor leaders in any way, how plauſible ſoever, that you have not well-grounded aſſurance, is warranted by the word, which while you obſerve as your Rule, will bee an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to the Lord, and you, while you live, and peace of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:54315:7"/>to you, when you come to dye, when all elſe you do, not concurrent herewith, will leave you under ſorrow, ſhame, and a blot that will nor bee wiped away.</p>
            <p>In the next place I deſire to conſider the <hi>beſt pleas</hi> I have met with by any of the Army in their own vindication; as firſt, they ſay <hi>all Governments are lawful,</hi> and ſo that by a Protector, and therefore that was not <hi>their ſin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Anſwer, How far a Government by a <hi>King</hi> or <hi>Protector</hi> is in its own nature <hi>lawful,</hi> or <hi>unlawful,</hi> I ſhall not here diſpute, but it ſatisfies mee that the introducing both the one and the other, hath been <hi>declared Treaſon by a Law of the Land</hi> that wee have as much reaſon to reverence and adhere to (conſidering the reaſons upon which it is grounded) as moſt Laws extant; to which let mee alſo add, the <hi>full concurrence</hi> of the Army there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, with their <hi>expreſt abhorrence</hi> of the contrary, ſtated by the Army, ſometimes upon tranſcendent grounds, to a Law of the Land, as is to bee ſeen in their <hi>Muſcellborough</hi> declaration in the year 50. all which conſidered, together with what <hi>God hath ſpoken</hi> ſince in oppoſition to ſuch a practice, makes it very neer of kin to a thing <hi>unlawful</hi> at leaſt for this Army to bring in ſuch a Government.</p>
            <p>But ſecondly, It is ſaid that theſe Governments were not <hi>of choice,</hi> but <hi>of neceſſity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Anſwer, So you ſay, but how or to whom that <hi>neceſsity appears</hi> beſide your ſelves, is a queſtion; when you are willing to <hi>ſubmit</hi> this point to the <hi>judgement</hi> of more unbiaſſed perſons, I hope you will bee heard, and till then, not expect to bee belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved.</p>
            <p>But thirdly, you ſay your <hi>aims</hi> and <hi>ends</hi> were good.</p>
            <p>Anſwer, What your <hi>ends</hi> were, the Lord <hi>knows,</hi> and will ere long let you and us <hi>know better;</hi> but <hi>good ends</hi> for the moſt part make but <hi>bad</hi> and <hi>unwarrantable Rules</hi> to act by; and ſo far as men may <hi>rationally gueſs</hi> at your <hi>ends,</hi> by your <hi>means</hi> you uſe towards them, they were not like to bee <hi>very good;</hi> and of this you wanted not <hi>warnings</hi> from all parts, but you would not then hear.</p>
            <p>Again, though you in the <hi>first part</hi> you acted under a <hi>ſingle perſon</hi> might have ſomething of a colour of <hi>good ends</hi> in what you
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:54315:7"/>did, yet ſure you had <hi>none ſuch</hi> for your <hi>ſecond part</hi> under your <hi>ſecond ſingle perſon;</hi> or if you ſhall yet ſay, you did judge that alſo a <hi>likely way</hi> and <hi>means</hi> to thoſe <hi>good ends,</hi> will not all ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional men in theſe three Nations riſe up at once and conclude you as a company of the <hi>moſt unfit men</hi> in <hi>England</hi> to <hi>judge</hi> in caſes of like kinde in future, who are ſubject to ſuch <hi>groſs mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtakes,</hi> wherein our lives, liberties and eſtates are concerned? and how would the <hi>ſenſe</hi> of your <hi>miſcarriage formerly,</hi> if it were <hi>right</hi> upon you, make you dread <hi>like paths,</hi> which you <hi>now not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding,</hi> as <hi>fearleſly</hi> as ever are <hi>running</hi> towards.</p>
            <p>But fourthly, You ſay you <hi>have repented,</hi> and indeavour to <hi>evince it</hi> by, Firſt, your <hi>diſſolving</hi> that Parliament called by <hi>Richard Cromwell.</hi> Secondly, In <hi>throwing down</hi> him.</p>
            <p>Anſwer, Whether thoſe actions had <hi>more of ſin or repentance in them,</hi> your preingagements conſidered, remains a queſtion with ſome, though out of queſtion with others, eſpecially as to you <hi>chief Commanders;</hi> and to the <hi>latter</hi> of them, whether you were herein <hi>ſo guilty,</hi> as you would now <hi>bee thought</hi> to bee, let the <hi>Arguments uſed</hi> by ſome of you to him, at that time, pleading your <hi>neceſſity</hi> from others, more than <hi>willingneſs</hi> in your ſelves to that work, ſpeak; though I beleeve indeed you were minded to <hi>attempt</hi> ſomewhat of <hi>alteration</hi> in his Counſel, as you were neerly concerned, in point of reputation, and other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, at that time to do; as alſo that you were <hi>providentially</hi> carried upon <hi>thoſe leggs</hi> on which you went, whither ſome of you <hi>would not</hi> have gone; and therefore at that time in the <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Council</hi> of Officers you did <hi>plead hard</hi> for the <hi>ſingle Perſon,</hi> ſome of you; others to have but the <hi>name,</hi> when the <hi>thing</hi> it ſelf could not bee had, and thereby manifeſting your <hi>conſtant good affection</hi> to the laſt, loſing this ground but <hi>by inches,</hi> rather <hi>furiouſly</hi> driven off it, than <hi>fairly</hi> quitting it; ſo that upon the <hi>whole,</hi> this looks <hi>very unlike</hi> a peece of <hi>repentance</hi> in you the <hi>chief Officers;</hi> but if any have <hi>a ſhare</hi> more than others in <hi>this ſervice,</hi> it is the <hi>inferiour ranks</hi> of men in the Army, who <hi>ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned not</hi> after the <hi>ſimilitude</hi> of the <hi>chief Officers tranſgreſsion,</hi> in ſetting him up, though ſome were <hi>drawn,</hi> and others <hi>driven</hi> by them, to ſacrifice to him in thoſe wretched addreſſes, when up, but were much more <hi>willingly helpful,</hi> and <hi>truly joyful,</hi> in throwing him down.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:54315:8"/>
            <p> But fifthly, You ſay you <hi>acknowledged your evils</hi> to the late Parliament, when you brought them to ſit again.</p>
            <p>Anſwer, You did very <hi>generally</hi> and <hi>curſorily</hi> mention <hi>ſome</hi> of your <hi>wandrings,</hi> but how <hi>few</hi> of theſe many particulars afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned, with <hi>many more</hi> of like kinde chargeable upon you, is <hi>obſervable?</hi> and the <hi>more ſo,</hi> becauſe when any comes to ſpeak with you particularly, they uſually meet with that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon queſtion much in uſe amongſt that poor people in <hi>Mala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chies</hi> time, <hi>ſaying, Wherein have wee done ſo evil?</hi> And though demonſtrations are clear now, as they were then, yet it is as hard to convince you, as it was them; and therefore that I might (if the will of the Lord were) a little help you in this main point of <hi>Repentance,</hi> upon the truth of which, and your being renewed, depends ſo much in this caſe; I therefore would a little treat you on this ſubject.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Repentance,</hi> when in truth, I take, doth conſiſt in theſe fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing particulars, <hi>viz.</hi> 1 <hi>Conviction,</hi> 2 <hi>Humiliation,</hi> 3 <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion,</hi> And 4 <hi>Forſaking ſin confeſſed,</hi> and would intreat you <hi>ſeriouſly to conſider</hi> this firſt part, to wit, <hi>Conviction;</hi> and ask your ſouls this <hi>ſingle queſtion,</hi> which the Lord will one day ask you, <hi>viz. Have you indeed been convinced, that you have wandred out of the way, with the cauſes, effects, and degrees thereof, and ſinful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of your ſo wandring,</hi> with reſpect to ſome <hi>Rule,</hi> or <hi>Rules</hi> of the Law by you <hi>tranſgreſſed</hi> herein, and what thoſe <hi>Rules are;</hi> as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo what is the <hi>nature</hi> of <hi>your ſin</hi> towards <hi>God,</hi> towards <hi>Men,</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards thoſe <hi>without,</hi> thoſe <hi>within,</hi> thoſe under <hi>your charge;</hi> as alſo thoſe that have been <hi>impriſoned, oppreſt, afflicted, derided,</hi> and <hi>ſcorned,</hi> by you, or ſome of you, for their indeavouring to bee <hi>faithful to the Lord,</hi> and his intereſt in this <hi>back-ſliding day?</hi> if you are rightly <hi>convinced,</hi> you will <hi>ſee your ſin,</hi> in theſe its ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral aſpects; for as the Spirit of the Lord <hi>convinceth clearly,</hi> ſo as no light doth like it, ſo it <hi>convinceth</hi> very <hi>particularly</hi> and <hi>ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> and uſually laies the ſoul <hi>convinced</hi> under the <hi>weight</hi> of its <hi>ſin,</hi> in its <hi>ſeveral aggravations,</hi> as it reſpects ſome <hi>Rule</hi> or <hi>Rules</hi> tranſgreſſed by it, and ſo renders <hi>ſin</hi> exceeding <hi>ſinful,</hi> Rom. 7.13. Now, have you been <hi>ſo convinced?</hi> hath that deluge of diſhonour brought upon the <hi>Name of the Lord,</hi> thoſe ſtains, blemiſhes, and blaſphemies brought upon that <hi>bleſſed cauſe of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:54315:8"/>God?</hi> together with that ignominy, contempt and cruelty caſt upon, and exerciſed towards many of thoſe poor unworthy wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes to the Lord and his work, in this day of declining, been with <hi>weight</hi> upon your hearts, yea or no? if not, ſure you are yet very far from <hi>thorow convictions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 As to your <hi>Humiliation,</hi> that alwaies <hi>attends true convi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,</hi> and includes <hi>contrition,</hi> as <hi>Zach.</hi> 12.10, 11, 12. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 7.16. Have you been at this work, <hi>families</hi> apart, your <hi>wives</hi> apart, and <hi>each ſoul</hi> apart, <hi>mourning bitterly</hi> over your tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, as an Army? if ſo, what means thoſe ſleighty <hi>extenuating expreſsions</hi> concerning your <hi>ſin,</hi> when ſpoken of? as alſo the <hi>ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence</hi> of you <hi>Leaders</hi> (who have <hi>lead</hi> in <hi>tranſgreſsion</hi>) in your daies of <hi>ſeeming ſolemn mourning</hi> before the Lord? you either <hi>contenting</hi> your ſelves, that ſome amongſt you ſpeak largely in your names, leaving you to your liberty of aſſent or diſſent (which you may poſſibly think you have) in ſuch eaſes, or elſe otherwiſe <hi>diſcovering heart-riſings</hi> againſt others, uſing plainneſs amongſt you, which you brook not ſo well; bee plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to read <hi>Davids</hi> practice in ſuch a caſe, a King and Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, not inferiour to any of you, 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 2.8. <hi>And David ſaid unto God, I have ſinned greatly, becauſe I have done this thing.</hi> And <hi>verſ.</hi> 17. <hi>Is it not I that commanded this people to bee numbred? Even I it is that have ſinned, and done evil in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, but as for theſe ſheep, what have they done? let thine hand, I pray thee, O Lord my God, bee on mee, and on my Fathers houſe, but not on thy people, that they ſhould bee plagued.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3 To that of <hi>confeſsion,</hi> which ought to bee <hi>particular</hi> and <hi>pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick,</hi> where <hi>evils</hi> have been ſo, <hi>Lev.</hi> 5.5. <hi>And it ſhall bee when bee ſhall bee guilty in one of theſe things, that hee ſhall confeſs that hee hath ſinned in that THING.</hi> Ezra 10.11. <hi>Now therefore make confeſsion unto the Lord God of your Fathers, and do his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and ſeparate your ſelves from the people of the Land, and from the ſtrange wives; then all the Congregation anſwered and ſaid with a loud voice, As thou haſt ſaid, ſo muſt wee do, but the people are many, and it is a time of much rain, and wee are not able to ſtand without, neither is this a work of one day or two, for wee are many that have tranſgreſſed in this thing.</hi> Act. 26.10, 11. <hi>Which thing I alſo did in Jeruſalem, and many of the Saints
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:54315:9"/>did I ſhut up in priſon, having received authority from the chief Prieſts, and when they were put to death, I gave my voice againſt them, and I puniſhed them oft in every Synagogue, and compel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led them to blaſpheme; and being exceedingly mad againſt them, I perſecuted them even to ſtrange Cities.</hi> Where is now this <hi>free, full, publick, particular confeſsion</hi> of yours? <hi>James</hi> 5.16. <hi>Confeſs your faults one to another, and pray one for another that you may bee hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led.</hi> This is <hi>the way</hi> that God will bee glorified, by perſons that have ſo <hi>publickly diſhonoured</hi> him, as you have done in your <hi>publick actions.</hi> Ezek. 44.10. And the Levites that went a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtray; <hi>When Iſrael went aſtray, which went aſtray away from mee after their Idols, they ſhall even bear their iniquities,</hi> v. 13. <hi>They ſhall bear their ſhame, and their abominations which they have committed.</hi> Take heed therefore of <hi>conſulting with fleſh and blood</hi> in this caſe; it is a <hi>hard leſſon</hi> for perſons in that port and degree in the world that you are in; but this is a part of that <hi>great leſſon</hi> of ſelf-denial, wherein <hi>every croſs</hi> that lies in the way of <hi>duty,</hi> muſt bee taken up by you; for if you have <hi>ſinned,</hi> you muſt <hi>riſe out</hi> of it in the <hi>way</hi> of God, or bee <hi>ruined</hi> by it; for hee will aſſuredly <hi>diſtrain</hi> for his glory that you will not give him.</p>
            <p n="4">4 As to your <hi>forſaking of ſin,</hi> that muſt not onely bee <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaking ſuch particular</hi> acts of <hi>ſin,</hi> which its poſſible have <hi>forſaken you,</hi> and you are <hi>not capable</hi> of committing thoſe individual acts again; but a <hi>departing from all</hi> of that kinde, yea of every kinde; and in this give mee leave once more to ask you; what are you doing herein? are you not again, inſtead of <hi>forſaking, fallen,</hi> and <hi>falling,</hi> into ſome of your <hi>old ſteps,</hi> that yet you would bee deemed to have <hi>repented of?</hi> elſe, why did you (not long ſince) come before the Lord in a <hi>very ſolemn day,</hi> profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing you were there like a company of <hi>poor children</hi> that knew not <hi>one ſtep</hi> of your way, to inquire of the Lord a <hi>right way,</hi> when before your coming there, you had <hi>reſolved of;</hi> ſo, <hi>conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable a part</hi> of your way, as the conduct of your Army; and that not for that time onely, as was then your pretence (which had been ſomewhat more tollerable) and whether not alſo of that rare <hi>compoſition ſince</hi> called the <hi>Committy of ſafety?</hi> you may do well to conſider; at leaſt whether in any rational mans judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:54315:9"/>the conſtitution of it conſidered, it can bee thought to bee the product of ſuch a <hi>ſolemn daies ſeeking the Lord</hi> for di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection; and is not your <hi>Army</hi> thus ſetled intended to bee <hi>influential</hi> to the <hi>framing</hi> your <hi>whole fabrick</hi> of Government now in the forge? and have not ſome of you already ſaid, that if it <hi>pleaſe not</hi> the people it is to bee offered to, they <hi>muſt bee pleaſed</hi> whether they will or not, and yet <hi>pretenſions of all freedome</hi> to bee uſed towards all good people? yea, I have been told by ſome of you, that you intended to do no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in your Government without <hi>advice had with good peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi> from all parts; hath that been, or is it intended? what is this other than the <hi>very firſt ſtep</hi> that <hi>Oliver Cromwell</hi> took? and who ſeeth not that <hi>this Army</hi> will yet again, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all its <hi>miſtakes</hi> be <hi>ſupream,</hi> admit nothing <hi>above it,</hi> or <hi>equal to it</hi> in all our greateſt concerns of life, liberty or eſtate? which muſt needs have this effect, to make <hi>good men nauciate</hi> it, or what is to bee done by it, as formerly; and then thoſe that will follow for the <hi>loaves,</hi> and tranſgreſs for a <hi>morſel of bread,</hi> ſhall again bee admitted in their ſphear of ſubſerviency, to a competent ſhare in this <hi>new gain'd dominion</hi> over the lives, liberties and eſtates of ſuch as cannot for conſcience ſake bow to ſuch an Image, when ſet up; and if this bee indeed <hi>forſaking ſin,</hi> then I underſtand it not; but this is your way, to which, if God will condeſcend to ſave by, you will ſerve him in, but not out of it, as I perceive; but know this, you muſt come to his waies, or bee broken by him; and deceive not your ſelves, I beſeech you, with pretenſions of doing good out of the way of it; though they may bee as <hi>high rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed</hi> in your imagination as <hi>Heaven,</hi> yet if not laid in <hi>deep humiliation</hi> for paſt tranſgreſſion, with <hi>thorow abhorring</hi> your ſelves in ſenſe of them, as alſo <hi>declining all paths</hi> that lead to the like in future, they will prove but <hi>abortive,</hi> and like a houſe built upon the ſand, that will aſſuredly fall, and great will bee the fall of it; and therefore ſince its moſt certain you <hi>cannot prosper</hi> in any work in your hands, till the Lord have accompliſhed this great work of <hi>unfeigned repentance</hi> upon your hearts, conſider your waies, and ſee if the Lord hath <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered</hi> you to this <hi>path</hi> of his <hi>good pleaſure,</hi> manifeſt it, and
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:54315:10"/>bleſs him for it; and if not, take heed of <hi>pretending</hi> to it, but rather <hi>confeſs</hi> your <hi>ſin,</hi> and give glory to the Lord, who hath ſaid, Hee will indeed bee ſanctified by all that draw neer to him, and before all the people hee will bee glorified; and truly, till you are taught to glorifie him in this way of his, that leading, guiding preſence of God, in relation to his work in your hands, will <hi>not bee with</hi> you, but will <hi>certainly and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly depart</hi> from you; and oh that I could ſay it were not <hi>al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready departed,</hi> as from <hi>Saul</hi> of old, cauſing you to <hi>labour</hi> in the <hi>fire</hi> for vanity, and run out of one fire into another, which is <hi>too viſibly</hi> your <hi>portion</hi> at this day; and <hi>baſe fears of man</hi> (for want of a Spirit of Faith, as formerly to make the Lord your fear, and your dread) are upon you, cauſing you to make <hi>undue haste</hi> many times; and the ſpirit of <hi>rage and madneſs</hi> of the Nations, riſing againſt you, cannot bee <hi>kept down</hi> by the ſpirit that yet appears to act you, but it <hi>grows and gains</hi> viſibly, yea <hi>runs</hi> upon you, <hi>teareth</hi> and <hi>rends</hi> you daily; and it is onely the <hi>Spirit of the Lord</hi> that can <hi>raiſe up a ſtandard</hi> to give check to ſuch <hi>floods;</hi> and till this <hi>Spirit more appears</hi> to act you, which will firſt carry you out of your <hi>own wiſdome, ſtrength,</hi> and every <hi>polluted path,</hi> and make you as <hi>poor children,</hi> not in <hi>word</hi> onely, but in <hi>truth,</hi> to ſay in the Lord you have all, and not elſewhere, you are, I am perſwaded, with other poor ones that follow you, like to <hi>wander in the wilderneſs;</hi> and which is moſt ſad, <hi>without a guide,</hi> till <hi>many,</hi> if not <hi>moſt</hi> of your <hi>carkaſſes fall</hi> there, or the Lord have <hi>purged out</hi> the rebels from among you; there is but <hi>one Name</hi> under Heaven that <hi>Salvation</hi> ſhall bee had from for Nations, as well as Souls, the <hi>cloſing</hi> with whom in his own way, as the wiſdome of the word directs to, would make you and theſe Nations alſo in their <hi>publick affairs hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py;</hi> and the <hi>contrary</hi> makes them <hi>miſerable:</hi> this is the <hi>founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> other than which (what ever any poor deluded flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering Courtiers have formerly prophanely ſaid of any of the projects of mens brains) <hi>can no man lay,</hi> nor any Nation or Nations with ſecurity by warrant from the word build upon; but their <hi>buildings</hi> will <hi>tumble,</hi> for hee hath ſaid, Hee <hi>will ſhake Nations</hi> thereby to <hi>remove</hi> what ever may bee <hi>ſhaken,</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:54315:10"/>till their <hi>deſire comes</hi> to him, who ſhall <hi>alone bear the glory,</hi> and not man or men with him.</p>
            <p>My poor advice is therefore to you; as ever you intend to <hi>proſper,</hi> bee <hi>wiſe,</hi> yee Rulers, Officers and Souldiers, <hi>kiſs the Son,</hi> not onely as <hi>a King</hi> and <hi>Saviour</hi> to your <hi>ſouls,</hi> but as <hi>King of Nations, leſt hee bee angry, and yee periſh from the way,</hi> for if his <hi>wrath bee kindled,</hi> and that <hi>but a little,</hi> onely <hi>bleſſed are they that truſt in him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And if you deſire thus to <hi>own</hi> him, do it by <hi>acknowledging</hi> him as your <hi>Law-giver,</hi> by your <hi>receiving and magnifying</hi> that <hi>Law,</hi> hee hath ſaid, hee <hi>will magnifie</hi> and <hi>make honourable,</hi> and <hi>caſting off</hi> the <hi>Laws</hi> of the <hi>Heathen,</hi> that ſerve for little elſe, but to <hi>lead</hi> into <hi>labyrinths;</hi> yea, <hi>Seek the Lord,</hi> and wait on him for light and wiſdome, and conſult his <hi>Word,</hi> and ſee if it bee not able thorowly to <hi>furniſh</hi> to every good work, beyond what any <hi>Laws of men</hi> can do; yea, this were the way to <hi>lay ſuch a Magna Charta,</hi> as would ſtand <hi>more ſure</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt any alterations, than any you can lay, both as to our rights, as men and Chriſtians, which is the great thing in conteſt, and would have a <hi>bleſſed inſtructing effect</hi> upon the <hi>adminiſtrators,</hi> as in <hi>Joſhua</hi> 1.8. As alſo upon them to whom they do <hi>adminiſter,</hi> teaching them the knowledge and fear of the Lord, which is ſo much wanting in theſe Nations at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent; when every mans <hi>particular intereſt</hi> ſhould lead him to conſult the <hi>Law of the Lord,</hi> in which his <hi>great intereſt</hi> is ſo much made known, and by beholding the <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> of <hi>that Law</hi> ſhould fall <hi>in love</hi> with it, and into a more <hi>frequent delightful meditation</hi> upon it, which being <hi>bleſt</hi> by the Lord, might bee <hi>inſtrumental</hi> to turn <hi>water</hi> into <hi>wine,</hi> to the <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verting</hi> of many poor ſouls that might begin at firſt, but with their own intereſt, beſides the <hi>civilizing effects,</hi> as to man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners amongſt men, this <hi>Law of the Lord</hi> hath a <hi>bleſſed tendency</hi> to beget, beyond any <hi>other Law</hi> whatſoever.</p>
            <p>But for you or others, that ſhall go after <hi>any other,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, or ſhort of him, or his righteous Laws, truly your <hi>ſorrows</hi> will bee <hi>multiplied,</hi> and you will <hi>lye down</hi> in them at the laſt; and though you may think you have <hi>strengthened</hi> your ſelves in the <hi>unitedneſs</hi> of your Army under ſuch a <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct,</hi>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:54315:11"/>yea much more <hi>ſtrengthened</hi> your arm of fleſh, by your new-raiſed <hi>Militia,</hi> or what elſe you may imagine, remember that the <hi>wrath of God is revealed from Heaven a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all unrighteouſneſs of men, who hold the truth in unrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs;</hi> And you have none of theſe <hi>coverings large enough</hi> to keep that from <hi>falling heavy</hi> upon you, to the ſudden diſſolving of every <hi>Covenant with death</hi> and <hi>Hell,</hi> and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flowing every <hi>hiding-place</hi> made up but of the <hi>refuge of lies,</hi> how like to truth ſoever they may bee.</p>
            <p>Theſe things being of ſome weight upon my heart, I durſt not but ſpeak to you, though I had arguments enough from a ſenſe of my own unworthineſs upon all accounts to have ſilenced mee, as well as my weakneſſe for ſuch an undertaking, in a ſervice in its own nature uſually un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acceptable, and much more may bee ſo with you for my ſake; but I have in this matter conſulted <hi>duty to the Lord,</hi> who I have indeavoured to eye in it; and ſecondly, to <hi>your ſouls,</hi> that I would fain ſee <hi>recovered</hi> out of ſuch <hi>deſtroying paths.</hi> I hope you will paſs by weakneſs herein, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept my intention, which hath been to ſerve you the moſt effectually I could. I have not troubled you oft in this kind, and for ought I know, it may bee the laſt ſervice of this na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture I may ever diſcharge to you as an Army, which if it bee of any uſe, I ſhall rejoyce, if otherwiſe, my ſoul I hope ſhall mourn on your behalfs (if it may bee to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent that miſery coming on you) and all of us with you, but that I truſt the Lord who knows how to deliver, when all other means fails, will bee a <hi>little Sanctuary</hi> to all that in ſincerity commit themſelves to him, deſiring to hate every falſe way, for hee hath ſaid it, that is able to perform it; <hi>Upon all the glory there ſhall bee a defence, and when the Enemy ſhall come in like a flood, the Spirit of the Lord ſhall lift up a ſtandard againſt him;</hi> Which I beleeve hee will yet do for his poor remnant, for his holy Names-ſake, and ſo do it as to aſtoniſh and confound enemies of all ſorts, greatly diſcover and ſhame falſe-hearted friends, take his people off from <hi>Idols,</hi> yea <hi>every pleaſant picture,</hi> and cauſe them to ſing to himſelf alone, as the God of their ſalvations, who remembers them in their low eſtate, becauſe his mercy endures for ever.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:54315:11"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
